(现在)
你说你喜欢聊天
You said you liked talking.
我记得
I remember that.
"在火堆前跟陌生人聊聊天"
"Little chats with a stranger by the fire."
你说那很像电影
You said it was like the movies.
然后你说你想要我有的一切
Then you said that you want everything that I have.
每一滴
Every last bit.
那我现在给你
Well, here it is.
每一滴
Every last bit.
(过去)
(清理)
你没有清理
You don't clear.
你没有
You don't.
不
No.
No, no.
你没有
You don't.
(清理)
不管多少天
It doesn't matter how many days...
或者多久
or how much time.
我们不该去那里
We weren't supposed to be there.
你拿着刀
You had the knife.
你拿着枪
You had the gun!
你该那样的
You were supposed to.
你知道你该那样的
You know you were supposed to.
别撒谎
Don't lie.
你心知肚明
You know.
你知道你该那样的
You know that you were supposed to!
《行尸走肉》
(清理)
对不起
I'm s-- I'm sorry.
对不起  对不起
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
不  对不起
No! I'm sorry.
你没有  你没有
You don't. You don't.
你没有  你知道你没有
You don't! You know you don't!
(毫无意义的行为)
(这不是那里)
(清理)
你还是同一个人
You're still the same.
你还在继续
You're-- you're still doing it.
你知道那是什么
You know what it is.
你能离羊远点吗
Can you step away from the goat?
她不是你的  我还需要她
She's not yours. I still need her.
我还在想办法做奶酪
I'm still figuring out how to make cheese.
不如你把枪放下  我们聊聊
Why don't you put the gun down and we'll talk?
吃点炸豆丸子
Have some falafel?
看起来你有阵子没吃东西了
Looks like you haven't eaten for a while.
真的  放下步枪  我们聊聊
Really, put down the rifle, let's talk.
我们肯定能和平解决
I'm sure we can work this out.
好吧  最后一次机会
Okay, last chance.
放下枪  离开小屋
Lower your gun, step away from the cabin.
抱歉
Sorry.
你叫什么
What's your name?
杀了我
Kill me.
这名字真蠢
Well, that's a stupid name.
很危险
It's dangerous.
你该换个名字
You should change it.
杀了我
Kill me.
Kill me!
杀了我
杀了我  杀了我
Kill me! Kill me!
(平静的艺术)
杀了我
Kill me.
我叫伊斯特曼
My name's Eastman.
没事的  塔比瑟
It's okay, Tabitha.
该死
Aw, shit.
这是你的
It's yours.
抢走吧
Take it.
不是你的就是他的
It's yours or his.
所以抢走吧
So you take it.
19小时里有16小时都躺在地上
16 hours in 19 on the floor.
你知道那是什么
You know what it is.
你对我开枪  我却给你吃东西
You shot at me. I fed you.
请不要伤害她
Please don't hurt her.
晚安
Good night.
19小时里有16小时都躺在地上
16 hours in 19 on the floor.
那...
Oh, that is--
真难吃
Oh, that's terrible!
天啊  那真
That-- oh, God, that is--
那真难吃
that is terrible.
我只是想等一阵子  然后再跟你聊天
I just wanted to wait a little while before we talked.
我来自亚特兰大
I'm from Atlanta.
我是犯罪心理学家
I'm a forensic psychiatrist.
政府雇我来评估
The state employed me to determine
一些做过坏事的人出狱后
if certain people who did very bad things would do them again
会不会重蹈覆辙
if they were released from prison.
之前那是我的工作  现在我住在这里
That was my job. Now I live here.
因为全国和世界的状态
Because of the state of the state and the whole world.
你之前是做什么的  现在呢
What did you do or what do you do now?
我清理
I clear.
那是什么意思
What the hell does that mean?
行尸  人类
Walkers, people,
只要有东西靠近我
anything that gets anywhere near me,
我就杀了他们
I kill 'em.
我清理
I clear.
为什么
Why?
只有那样我才能活下来
Because that's why I'm still here.
这...
Well...
这是我听过的最扯的屁话
that's the biggest load of horseshit I ever heard.
你的午餐
Here's your lunch.
那是创伤后遗症
It's PTSD.
你受过精神创伤  是不是
You've been through trauma, right?
你看见我棍子顶端的血迹了吗
You see that blood on the end of my stick?
尖的那一头上的
At the sharp end?
那是两个人的
That was two men.
也许是父亲和儿子
Father and son, maybe.
我捅穿了其中一个的喉咙
I stabbed one through the throat.
他就那样...
He just...
喉咙里插着棍子倒在了地上
fell to the ground with it stuck in him
他还试图呛着血呼吸
trying to breathe through the blood.
我勒死了另一个
Other one I strangled.
没用绳子  徒手杀死的
No rope, just my hands.
那发生在我到这里的前一天
That was the day before I came here.
也许...
Maybe--
也许就是同一天
maybe the same day.
我...我不知道
I-- I don't know.
我之前就是干那个的
But that's what I did.
现在也是
That's what I do.
你杀过很多人吗
You killed a lot of people?
没错
Yes.
他们威胁到你了或是攻击你了吗
They were threatening you, attacking you?
不是所有人
Not all of them.
你救过人吗
You save anyone?
你救过
You saved people.
毫无意义的行为
Pointless acts.
所有人都转化了
Everybody turns.
我之前看到了一枚婚戒
I saw a wedding ring.
你有过爱人  是不是
You had someone you loved, didn't you?
有孩子吗
Children?
你爱他们
You loved them.
你肯定是很爱他们才会变成这样
You loved them a lot if you're like this.
你目睹了悲剧的发生
You saw it happen.
然后你就变成了这样  是不是
That's how this started, right?
所有悲剧都在你眼前一次又一次上演
It's all happening right in front of your eyes over and over.
你的身体在这里
Your body's here,
但心还在那里
but your mind is still there.
有一扇门
There's a door
你想穿过它  然后离开
and you want to go through it to get away from it,
所以你穿过了
so you do
但它却将你领回了那一刻
and it leads you right back to that moment.
然后你又看见了那扇门
And you see that door again
你知道它不起作用
and you know it won't work,
但是  管他呢  也许会有用的
but, hell, maybe it'll work.
所以你又踏入了那扇门
So you step through that door
然后每次都回到那可怕的一刻
and you're right back in that horrible moment every time.
你仍然每次都能感觉得到
You still feel it every time.
所以你就不想再打开那扇门了
So you just want to stop opening that door.
你只是坐在里面
So you just sit in it.
但是我向你保证
But I assure you,
其中一扇门可以出去  我的朋友
one of those doors leads out, my friend.
我没有任何朋友
I don't have any friends.
好好认识下我吧
Get to know me.
我会杀了你的
Oh, I'm gonna kill you.
-为什么  -因为我必须清理
- Why? - Because I have to clear.
瞧  这才是问题所在  你不必的
See, that's the thing. You don't.
杀人不是我们的本性
We're not built to kill.
我们生来没有利爪  獠牙和针刺
We don't have claws or fangs or armor.
患了创伤后遗症的老兵
Vets that came back with PTSD,
那不是因为我们愿意杀人
that didn't happen because we're comfortable with killing.
我们不愿意  我们不可能愿意
We're not. We can't be.
我们有感情  我们是血脉相连的
We feel. We're connected.
我评估过超过825个
You know, I've interviewed over 825 people
做过坏事的人
who've done terrible things.
只遇到过一个真正的恶人
I've only met one evil person.
有些人生来脑袋不好使
Some of them were born with bad brains.
有些人是因为成长环境
Some of them got sick along the way.
剩下的不过是受过创伤的人
The rest were just damaged people.
像你一样受到创伤  但是他们能够痊愈
Traumatized themselves like you, but they could heal.
有些好的彻底  有些不彻底
Some more, some less,
但是他们能痊愈  我们都能
but they can. We all can.
我知道的
I know it.
万物循环往复  一报还一报
It's all a circle and everything gets a return.
门是敞开的
The door is open.
就是这扇牢门  是开着的
That door right there. The cell door, it's open.
我不久前把钥匙扔进河里了
I threw the key in the river a while back.
我不会再关着你了
I'm not gonna hold you anymore.
我无法阻止你  去清理吧
I can't stop you. Go, clear.
或者留下  睡在沙发上
Or stay, crash on the couch,
我们试图帮你找到其他出路
and we'll try to find you another way.
门是开着的
The door's open.
一直都开着
It's been open all along.
留下或离开
You stay or you go.
你只有这两个选择
Those are the choices.
我不会允许你杀了我
I will not allow you to kill me.
我不会允许的
I will not allow that.
别
Don't!
住手
Stop.
我给了你两个选择
I gave you two choices.
糟糕
Oh, shit.
杀了我
Kill me.
我给了你两个选择
I gave you two choices.
门或沙发
The door or the couch.
是合气道
That was Aikido.
就是我之前击败你所用的那招
That's how I kicked your ass earlier.
或者说用那招扭转了你的身体
Well, that's how I redirected your ass.
我帮国家评估的犯人
The people in prison I evaluated for the state,
我听到的故事
the stories I heard,
犯人们做的事
the things these people did.
有一天晚上  我喝了8罐啤酒后
One night, my five-year-old daughter
我5岁的女儿看到我在车库哭
found me crying in the garage after about eight beers.
我告诉她  我心里有点难受
Told her I wasn't feeling too good.
她就给了我这个
She gave me this.
是她那天在学校联欢时赢的
She had won it at a carnival at school that day.
她说  这个会给我带来好运  并让我好受些
She said it'd make me lucky and I'd feel better.
第二天早上我看到一张合气道的传单
The next morning I found a flyer for aikido.
想不到还真管用
Damn thing worked.
你妻子和女儿
Your wife and your daughter...
她们死了
they're dead.
合气道
It was aikido.
会有帮助的
It'll help.
如果我们要踏上旅途  你显然需要帮助
And you obviously need help if we're gonna make this trip.
不能一直只有你和我走下去
Can't just be me and you to the end.
你太不健谈了
You're a shit conversationalist,
而我又不能独自上路
and I can't make this trip by myself.
上路去哪
A trip where?
我也不知道
I have no idea.
晚安
Good night.
这草味儿有点太像人造草坪的了
Grassy notes are a little too Astroturf,
但还是有潜力的
but there's potential here.
潜力总是有的
There is always potential.
有生命的地方就有潜力
Where there's life, there's potential.
我吃素食有一阵子了
I've been a vegetarian for a while now.
我之前还担心那头该死的山羊
I was afraid that damn goat
会把我变成严格的素食主义者
was gonna make me a vegan.
我不杀生  但我暂时不打算放弃巧克力
I don't kill, but I'm not giving up on chocolate any time soon.
你可能注意到了  我不打算放弃巧克力甜饼
You might notice I'm not giving up on the Goo Goo Clusters.
你的菜单上会一直有它
They're gonna remain on the menu.
你应该尝尝  很好吃的
You should try one. They're good.
好了  你是活人  有点生气吧
Come on, you're alive. Live a little.
我们应该出门
We should go out.
虽然这里有很多东西
We got a lot here,
但我们还是应该为旅途找些必需品回来
but we should scavenge some things up for the trip.
你来吗
You coming?
我出去时  你能帮我看着塔比瑟吗
Will you watch Tabitha while I'm gone?
能帮我这个忙吗
Can you do that for me?
(平静的艺术)
(合气道即不杀之道)
(尽管大部分武道流派都规定不杀生  但是同时也默许为正义而取人性命)
(然而在合气道中  我们完全避免杀戮)
(即使面对最邪恶的人)
你弄坏了一株番茄
Well, you maimed a tomato plant,
但你今天似乎救了山羊  我的朋友
but it looks to me like you saved a goat today, my friend.
谢谢
Thank you.
有进步
Progress.
稍等
Just a second.
有两件事
A and B.
首先  你弄坏了栅栏
A-- you broke the garden fence,
糟蹋了一株完好的番茄
laid waste to a perfectly good tomato plant.
你得负责修好
You got to fix it.
其次  跟我来
B-- follow me.
我把你的矛修好了
Fixed your spear.
要义在于扭转
It's about redirecting.
规避
Evading.
甚至是关心对手的安危
And actually caring about the welfare of your opponent.
所以你要关爱自己
So you have to care about yourself.
你要相信你的命很宝贵
You have to believe your life is precious,
所有的生命都是宝贵的
that all life is precious.
你要扭转你的想法
You have to redirect those thoughts,
和与此相悖的过往经历
the history that tells you otherwise.
往事不可追
What we've done, we've done.
我们通过前进来规避过去
We evade it by moving forward
秉承着绝不再犯的原则
with a code to never to do it again.
为从前赎罪
To make up for it.
依然接受自己曾经的样子
To still accept what we were.
接受所有人
To accept everyone.
保护所有人
To protect everyone.
从而保护自己
And in doing that, protect yourself.
创造平静
To create peace.
你屋里为什么会有一个牢笼
Why do you have a cell in your cabin?
我和妻子一起建造了这个地方
Built this place with my wife
就在我女儿出生之前
a while before our daughter was born.
那时候还没有牢笼
It didn't have a cell back then.
只是客厅的一部分
That was just the other side of the living room.
我评估过超过800个男人和25个女人
In my job I interviewed over 800 men and 25 women
都做过可怕的事
convicted of awful things.
源自人性最黑暗处的罪行
Stuff from the darkest part of the human soul.
我当时在评估一个
I was evaluating a man
名为克赖顿·达拉斯·威尔顿的男人
by the name of Crighton Dallas Wilton.
这名字  听起来仿佛他拥有一家石油公司
Name like that, sounded like he should own an oil company
戴一顶大帽子  克赖顿·达拉斯·威尔顿
and wear a big hat-- Crighton Dallas Wilton.
尽管犯了可怕的恶行  他还是有了假释的机会
Despite doing some truly unspeakable acts, he was up for parole.
他是我见过的最讨喜的人之一
And he was one of the most damn likable people I had ever met.
他会说好话  参加了心理治疗
He said all the right things, he went to therapy.
他给监狱委员会写信申请
He wrote letters to the prison board to start a program
一个种花的项目  把花摆在等候室里
to grow flowers for the waiting rooms
公立医院里  疗养院里
in state hospitals, rest homes.
但我一眼看穿了他
And I saw right through him.
看穿了他是一个真正的变态
Saw that he was a true psychopath,
他知道怎么操纵别人  他深谙此道
that he knew how to play people, exactly how to play people.
我当时在食堂旁边和他谈话
I was interviewing him next to the cafeteria.
那地方充满工业化披萨味儿
The place smelled of industrial pizza.
他们在给地板打蜡
They were polishing the floor.
我有一半时间得喊着问问题
I had to shout my questions half the time.
有那么一瞬间
And there was this moment.
不记得具体对话了
Can't even remember the exchange.
那一瞬间我发现
But right then I knew
克莱顿明白我看穿他的真实面目了
that Crighton knew that I knew exactly what he was.
之前他所说所做的一切
Everything he had said, done to hide away
向别人隐瞒自己的努力
what he was from everyone, from himself,
全都白费了  然后...
just slipped away, and...
那个蹲过十年牢的模范囚犯站起来
and that model prisoner of 10 years stood up,
面带微笑
smiled,
冲着我的脸狠狠地来了一拳
and just cracked me across the face.
他的拳头就像石块一样
His fist felt like a rock.
然后他压在我身上  隔壁的地板打蜡器
Then he was on top of me and the floor polisher next door
掩盖住了所有声音
was thudding out every sound.
我...
And I--
我看到了他的脸
and I saw his face,
他的眼睛
his-- his eyes,
他的恶念
his evil.
他撕下了面具
Mask had slipped.
他会当场把我打死
And he was gonna kill me right then and there
因为他知道我会确保他不再出狱
because he knew I would make sure he would never get out again.
握臂反击
Arm bar counter
这是僵持不下时使用的招式
for being choked from a pinned position.
合气道
Aikido.
我不是学来防身的
I wasn't taking it for self-defense,
但这的确救了我的命
but it saved my life.
我还确保了他再也不会出狱
And I got to make sure he never got out again.
总得试试
Well, got to try.
他越狱了
He got out.
找对了人  帮了他一把
Talked to the right people who got him the right things
他就越狱了  但他不是为了逃跑
and he broke out, but it wasn't to escape.
克莱顿·达拉斯·威尔顿去了我家
Crighton Dallas Wilton went to my home
杀了我的妻子  女儿和儿子
and killed my wife, my daughter, and my son.
他浑身沾着他们的血
He walked down the street to the police station
径直走进了街角的警局
around the corner covered in their blood.
他自首了
He surrendered.
他说他越狱唯一的理由
Said the only reason he broke out
就是毁掉我的生活
was to destroy my life.
过了一年
A year passed...
他还在种地
and he was still working those plots.
他们就让他种地
They just let him work those plots
在85号公路边
by the roads out by 85,
种菊花  勿忘我
grow chrysanthemums, forget-me-nots.
我建造了那个牢笼  一心想
I built that cell with the full intention
把克莱顿·达拉斯·威尔顿带到这里
of bringing Crighton Dallas Wilton here,
把他关在栅栏后面  让他活活饿死
putting him behind those bars and watching him starve to death.
你成功了吗
And did you?
我开始相信
I have come to believe
所有生命都是宝贵的
that all life is precious.
即使是那种人吗
Even for a man like that?
他对你  对你的家人
Who did that to you?
做出了那种事
To your family?
我开始相信
I have come to believe
所有生命都是宝贵的
that all life is precious.
所以我们才能在这吃燕麦汉堡
That's why we're having oatmeal burgers.
你很擅长嘛
You're good at it.
我是说扭转想法
Redirecting.
我们需要更多的器材
We need more gear.
防水布  撬棍
Tarp, crowbar.
我想我们可以去一些沿海岛屿
I'm thinking we could try for the islands off the coast.
人们也许去那里避难了
I think people could have gone there.
至少  我们能看看海滩
Hell, at the very least, we could see the beach.
怎么了
What is it?
我知道在哪能找到那些东西
I know where we can find all that.
(清理)
(你只有一次机会)
(毫无意义的行为)
(这不是那里)
你失去了谁
Who did you lose?
我的妻子和儿子
My wife and son.
你失去的人
Who you lost.
他们的名字
Their names.
珍妮和德韦恩
Jenny and Duane.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
永远不要感到抱歉
Don't ever be sorry.
现在训练
Forms, right now.
不要在这
Not here.
就现在
Right now.
你还会抱上孩子的
You're gonna hold a baby again.
交给你了
It's all yours.
该死  让开
Damn it, move!
我说了不要在这
I said not here.
你不该那样做
That wasn't for you to do.
你怎么能那样  你不该那样做
How could you do that? That wasn't for you to do!
你不能...
You can't just--
你不能干涉的
you can't just step in!
告诉我怎么样了
Tell me how it is.
告诉我怎么样了  告诉我
Tell me how it is! Tell me!
我们回家吧
Let's go home.
我哪都不去
I'm not going anywhere.
你给我回去
You're coming back.
你已经摆脱这里了
You are done with this.
你走出去了
You made it out.
杀了我
Kill me.
Kill me!
我说了不要在这
I said not here.
这才是问题所在  摩根
Well, that's the thing, Morgan.
这不是那里
Here's not here.
(毫无意义的行为)
谢谢你
Thank you.
她跑出去了
Oh, she got out.
她也发现了门是开着的
She figured out the door was open, too.
我没发现
I didn't figure it out.
是你告诉我的
You had to tell me.
很高兴你回来了
Glad you're back.
给
Here.
行了  快坐下歇会  不然要摔倒了
Come on, you sit down before you fall down.
(克莱顿·达拉斯·威尔顿)
如我所说  他们
Well, like I said, they...
让他在85号公路边上种地
let him work the plots beside 85.
即便是在他干出那事之后
Even after what he did.
因为他太他妈讨喜了
They let him because he was so damn charming.
我查到了作息表  静候时机
I found out the schedule, waited,
确保正确的人在工作
made sure the right people were working.
我很快地把他拽到我车里
I got him in my car quick
带他来了这
and brought him back here.
他们要是抓到我了  也没事
If they'd have caught me, it'd have been fine.
可能还更好
It'd have been better.
但我把他带到这来  他们也不知道去哪找
But I got him here and they didn't know where to look.
你得坐下
You gotta sit down.
好的
All right.
我没事
I'm okay.
我把他关到牢里
I put him in that cell...
把他活活饿死了
and I let him starve to death.
花了47天
It took 47 days.
然后我就自暴自弃了
And then I was gone.
我也曾跟你一样
I was where you were.
我也放弃了再打开那扇门
And I wasn't trying to open up the door anymore either.
我对他所做的
What I did to him,
没能让我得到内心的平静
it didn't give me any peace.
只有在我决定
I found my peace
再也不杀生后才找到了那份平静
when I decided to never kill again.
永不杀生
To never kill anything again.
当我决定解决这事时
When I decided to settle things,
我便回到亚特兰大自首
I went back to Atlanta to turn myself in.
那时我才知道世界末日了
That's how I found out the world ended.
但世界并没有末日
But the world hasn't ended.
有进步
Progress.
我女儿在我们家走廊墙上画的
My daughter drew this on the hallway wall of our house.
她以为我会生气
She thought I'd get mad.
我只是加了个画框
I just put a frame around it.
我回去后  发现我没法自首
After I went back, when I found out I couldn't turn myself in
因为已经没有警察了
because there was no one to turn myself in to,
我回到家把这从墙上割了下来
I went back home to cut this from the wall.
回来的时候车丢了
I lost the car on the way back.
我穿过三十英里的行尸群
I walked through 30 miles of the dead
只为了块墙画
for a piece of drywall.
这是我做过最恐怖的事
Scariest thing I ever did.
也是我做过最值的事
Best thing I ever did.
你可以留下
You can stay here.
这里有足够的食物  电力  很安全
You have enough food, power, security.
你下半生都可以住在这里
For the rest of your life, you could stay here.
但是你不该留下
But you shouldn't stay here.
恐怕不会再有你这么杰出的客人登门了
Can't expect such a splendid guest as yourself to show up.
你留在这里  会孤单一人
You stay here, you'll be alone.
你之前就很孤单
You were alone.
人才是最重要的
Everything is about people.
生命中一切有意义的事情都是为了人
Everything in this life that's worth a damn.
不该只有我  不该只有你
It couldn't be just me. It shouldn't be just you.
见鬼  现在连塔比瑟都死了
Hell, Tabitha's gone now.
我准备好了
I'm ready.
我那边的闭锁箱里有枪
I have a gun in the lockbox out there.
来
Here.
等等
Oh, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
但愿也能给你带来好运
Hope it's lucky for you, too,
不管你怎么决定
whatever you decide.
我已经决定了
I've decided.
(伊斯特曼)
(避难所和社区  欢迎所有人  抵达就能活命  终点站)
就是这样
And that's it.
每一滴都说了
Every last bit.
你觉得那一套对我管用吗
You think it can work out that way with me?
是的
Yes.
我觉得管用
I think it can.
也许吧
Maybe.
你注意到我有点发抖吗
You noticed I'm shaking a little?
有点流汗
Sweating a little?
天啊
Oh, man.
我在找到的照片上看到
I saw how settled this place was
这个地方多么安定
in the pictures I found.
我想这里也许有些东西
I thought maybe there'd be something here.
能疗伤的药
Medicine to help this.
但那是在你们的人赢了之前
But that was before you people won.
所以我知道我很可能会死
So I know I'm probably going to die.
但是如果我没死
But if I don't...
我必须得杀了你  摩根
I am going to have to kill you, Morgan.
我必须得杀了这里的每个人
I'm going to have to kill every person here.
每个人  包括孩子
Every one of them. The children, too.
就像你朋友伊斯特曼的孩子一样
Just like your friend Eastman's children.
这些是规矩
Those are the rules.
是我的原则
That's my code.
我想说我很抱歉
I'd say I'm sorry,
但是你说过的  对吧
but you said it, right?
永远不要感到抱歉
Don't ever be sorry.
开门
Open the gate!